Kia ora. Welcome.
All right. Welcome,
and thank you for making the effort to come in today. I'll just introduce myself.
I'm Greg O'Connor. I'm the chair of the Select-- of the Petitions Committee.
Good day. Grant McPeamy, the deputy chair.
Nice to meet you.
Carl Weggs. I'm in for the Honorable Andrew Bayly,
sir.
Kia ora. Welcome. Selwyn Maib Brown. Cheers. Good evening.
Yes. All right. So now,
we've got you for 10 minutes. We've read your submissions, very
good submission.
And we'd love to hear from you, reiterate your
points, and hopefully leave time for questions.
Yes.
Thank you.
Kia ora koutou. Good afternoon. My name is Aida.
I'm a founding member of the Iranian Solidarity Group New Zealand.
Thank you for this opportunity to present to the committee on our petition.
This is
Arman, Arman Askarami. Arman is a member of the
Iranian Solidarity Group New Zealand.
He's also a lawyer who's worked for the community law
space, who's worked in the community law space, especially in
refugee and immigration law. And I'm now going to hand over to
Arman to present to the committee our oral submission.
Thank you.
Awesome.
Welcome, Arman.
Thank you very much for the opportunity.
So,
as you would've seen in the written submission, the petition is
about a family reunification pathway for Iranian
New Zealanders.
And we're seeking something modeled on the same precedent that the special
Ukraine visa was issued in 2022.
In terms of context, obviously there's been a war that's been ongoing
since February 28th, and
prior to that, a lot of protests and a lot of violence and
repression.
Estimates vary, but
suggest that upwards of 25,000 bombs have been dropped
between the US and Israel over the last few months.
We've also seen
a lot of civilian infrastructure that's been targeted, including
hospitals, water desalination plants, electrical
grids, schools, including a primary school in which
more than 100 children were killed on the very first day.
Airports, train stations,
residential areas,
and although in the last few days there's been a pause
in the bombing,
the situation is still very uncertain.
There's still a lot of uncertainty and instability in terms of
what comes next, and it's very fragile and very possible that
we might see full-scale war again, and there's been a lot of
back-and-forth threats. Threats of war crimes, things of this
nature.
In terms of the human toll, we know that thousands have already been
killed from the war so far. We know that thousands more have been
wounded. We know that millions have been displaced,
according to the Red Cross.
And of course, millions more have been traumatized because that's what war
does.
And so overall, there is really a bleak situation right
now, and there is a lot of hardship,
and a humanitarian crisis. And I'd point to
even MFAT has advised do not travel
for Iran. So, clearly there's an acknowledgment
of the difficult situation at the moment.
And so in this context, what we are
seeking is for support for the Iranian New Zealand
community, the same way that Ukrainian New Zealanders were
supported when the war started over there.
And so we're seeking a family reunification pathway modeled on the same
precedent.
Iranian New Zealanders are ready, willing, and able to fulfill any
sponsorship undertakings that are required.
And we think the total number that would be impacted here would
be small, at most in the low thousands.
We note that for the Ukraine visa, there were
2,293 temporary visas, and
ultimately only 480 people who got residency
through this pathway. So not a huge amount, but it would have
a really
meaningful impact on the community here.
And I can say, the community here, it's been a very difficult
situation and
a lot of Iranian New Zealanders have felt isolated and withdrawn and
depressed and I think this type of action can
help with social cohesion and
help people feel seen, heard, and valued.
I note that in some of the responses, there's been reference to
Immigration New Zealand providing further information
in terms of a phone line or how to apply for visas.
And while we appreciate that,
we submit that that doesn't ultimately assist the
situation because for any temporary visa
application, the applicant must be a bona fide
applicant, which is someone who genuinely intends a temporary
stay. And with the circumstances of war and
humanitarian crisis, it's a Really huge
hurdle to persuade Immigration New Zealand that anyone
really does
genuinely intend a temporary stay.
There was also reference to special direction requests as
well. I can speak from my time working in
community law. Those special direction requests are
very onerous. They're completely discretionary and
granted on an ad hoc basis.
So not really a sustainable solution for the
community here. And everybody has a family member
or family members
that we're deeply worried about.
Aside from the family reunification pathway, we'd also included in the
petition
something about an automatic visa extension for those currently in
the country on temporary visas, which MBA had said there was
1,017 Iranians on temporary visas as of May
2026.
And automatic visa extensions have been done, for example, during the COVID
pandemic. So it's something that's been done before.
But again, it's not huge numbers here, but it would really make a huge
difference for the community here.
And ultimately, we're just seeking the same compassion and empathy
that was afforded to Ukrainian New Zealanders during their time of
hardship.
All right. Thank you. Can I ask a question?
You've highlighted the fact this would be largely temporary and that
people would presumably go back to Iran
at the end of the war or at the end of the regime.
Because presumably, there are two overriding reasons here
why people want to leave Iran. Correct me if I'm
wrong, but there's the regime and then there's the war.
So we would have envisioned a pathway for residency if
people sought that. So
not necessarily just a temporary visa for ...
And that was the same with the special Ukraine visa.
There was an option to apply for residency that was introduced, which I said
450 Ukrainians did that.
I mean, both of those factors are
causing
hardship, but right now the war is the
main,
causing the most urgency and anxiety and
stress for our community.
If the regime remains in place and the war ends,
will those that come out under any visa such as this
be punished when they go back or likely to be disadvantaged when they go back
to Iran?
I probably couldn't speak in absolutes in terms
of how it would happen. I
would hesitate to say that anyone who migrates out, there would be
retribution or retaliation just for them leaving the country and coming back
in. Ultimately, what the Iranian government
does, I can't really speak for their mindset and
I'm sure there's a lot of things going through their minds in terms of what they
factor, so I can't really
speculate too much about that.
Thank you very much. Celia.
Thank you. Thank you for coming in, and thank you for also
sharing the Iranian culture, particularly through Nowruz and
so on.
Thank you for having me.
And
I was just interested in a couple of things.
I was looking at the comparison with the Ukrainian visa.
It
was open for two years. It's now closed, but sadly, the war
there continues. So how useful do you
think that has been for the Ukrainian ...
I mean, you may not know. That's fine.
Yeah. I mean, I'm sure there's areas for improvement
in terms of how that was rolled out, and that was certainly the first of its
kind to be done here. I think the point that we're
ultimately making is that there was the will there to try
and create a pathway for that community to be able to
sponsor their loved ones and just to
provide some type of assistance.
And so that's kind of the key point that we wanted to make.
Thank you. If I may, another couple of questions.
Sure.
Sadly, events at the moment
are impacting a number of countries in the same geographic
area.
The Greens have called, for example,
for
visas for Palestinian
people. How do you see
us proceeding as a government with
the request from a number of different countries?
Yeah. I mean, I think it's a valid point to talk
about consistency in terms of responding to various
humanitarian crises around the world.
I know that World Vision had recently launched an emergency
protection framework in terms of creating-
Okay
... a sort of humanitarian visa category.
I think Australia has something similar.
I think those are
worthy efforts and worth genuine consideration, and
yeah, I have complete sympathy for the Palestinians advocating for
something similar or any other community affected by war and hardship
advocating for something similar.
Thank you.
All right.
Great.
Yeah, Tena Koutou, and thank you very much for the completeness of your
submission. In terms of the stories that each of the accounts that you had in your
written submission-
Mm
... how many of those were taken through your local electorate
MP to the Associate Minister for Immigration?
I couldn't tell you-
That's all right
... off the top of my head because we had the petition and then we had
the email address, and it was throughout the country.
So those individual stories are from a number of different electorates.
And so I haven't spoken personally with-
Okay
... those MP-
And we did send them information on contacting Erica
Stanford's office or local MPs.
Yeah.
We were hoping that they got in touch-
Sure
... but they may not have heard back.
Because we ourselves tried to set up a meeting with Erica
Stanford to talk to her about those cases and
about just the overall thing.
We
received an acknowledgement email, but it hasn't gone further than
that.
So what I would encourage, I'm a first-term MP, but as an electorate MP,
I've been
surprised. I don't know about you, Karl.
I'm in central Auckland, and well over
50% of my electorate weren't born in New Zealand.
So a lot of these issues, immigration issues, are real ones.
I would spend literally a quarter of my time on immigration cases as the
local electorate MP who knew that I'd end up becoming an immigration expert.
Mm.
And we work regularly with the Associate
Immigration Minister's office in reviewing precisely these
kinds of cases.
Mm.
And you'd be encouraged to see how many
cases are actually positively reviewed.
So it's-
Mm
... New Zealand's really unusual,
and this is particularly unusual within our constitutional arrangement, that the
Associate Immigration Minister has the unilateral
authority to grant visas
on the basis of personally reviewing the cases.
And I think that's what-- So what you're asking for here does actually
exist. It's just it sits in the personal discretion of the Associate Immigration
Minister, not the Immigration Minister.
Okay.
She doesn't actually have the constitutional authority.
Can I respond to that? And thank you for-
Yeah. Yeah, sure
... pointing that out. I've done a few special direction requests to the Associate
Minister from my time working at the Auckland-
Yeah
... I used to work at the Auckland Community Law Center.
Oh, right. In Mangere?
No, that's south Auckland. Auckland Central. That's where I used to work.
And I've had success and I've also not had success-
Yeah, sure
... with some of these special direction requests.
As you know, they're completely discretionary in terms-
Yes
... of the Associate Minister's power, and they're not required to give reasons in
terms of why.
Yeah.
I've found, and some of my colleagues and former colleagues have found,
that
there's often a better chance when it's related to someone who's currently present
in the country,
whether their status has become unlawful or whether their visa pathway is
insecure.
Yeah.
And so for family members who are on the other side of the
world. And also a lot of Iranians are internally
displaced as well.
Right.
So they're not technically refugees because a refugee is someone outside of
their home country with a UNHCR card.
It just makes things difficult. So I totally appreciate that point, but I don't
have confidence that we would be able to get the same types of outcomes
through special direction requests.
Yeah. No, I appreciate that. I totally understand, yeah, that obviously if there
was a special category that would be ideal.
But
just given-
Yeah
... as what my colleague was asking here, and this is the point that he can be
making in their response as well, is that there are, sadly,
with seemingly the world on fire, there are an
increasing number of places that are asking for the
same thing that you guys are asking for.
Which is why
I'm encouraged to hear that you're aware of that pathway and go for it.
It's just that within those ones there, there's just a lot of those.
Look, to me, based on my experience in the last couple of years, very compelling
cases to take to the Associate Immigration Minister.
Yeah.
All right. Look, well, thank you very much.
Don't ever underrate that you're obviously knocking on many
doors as you can.
And this is another way of making sure that
your, and that the stories
and particularly the situations of people you
represent and friends and family are known.
Don't underestimate that even though there mightn't be an instant tick
this box solution, that there
are various, as my colleague
Greg has pointed out, there are various ways that these things can
be
assisted, helped if not resolved.
So thank you very much for making the effort to come in.
Yeah. Thank you very much.
Thank you.
You're
welcome.
She can't make this time.
No. Okay.
We'll discuss this one afterwards.
New Zealand Post.
Oh, next.
Oh, thank you.
Yeah.
Next.
All right. All right. Welcome to the table.
Thank you.
Just you, John. You're
welcome to bring your colleague up with you if you-
Okay.
This is my brother-in-law, John Boys, a hospital chaplain for 25 years.
Ah, welcome.
So it's quite relevant that he's here when you hear what I've got to say.
Thank you.
Tena koutou.
Right. We've introduced you, you've heard our introductions, and give us an
outline-
Thank you
... the case, if you like, and then-
Yeah
... hopefully have time for questions.
So John Maynard, I'm the co-national president of the Postal Workers' Union,
and the union's petition and submissions have come to the Petitions Committee
driven by the frustration and despair of New Zealanders-
I just want to say now, John, that New Zealand Post will be on, are coming on
afterwards online.
That's fine.
And
are online now currently.
That's fine. Yeah, that's okay.
And come to us from the frustration and despair of
New Zealand Post customers asking posties why their mail is being
returned to senders, and the frustration of the posties explaining to their
customers that they've been instructed by the company to return their
particular mail to the sender because it's been addressed to their street
address.
After the police officer was struck and killed in Nelson on New Year's morning last
year, New Zealand Post policy was for the sympathy cards to be
returned to sender because the private bag number of the Nelson Police
Station was not on the sympathy card envelopes.
And this has been New Zealand Post policy since May 2024.
A card addressed to the emergency department of a city hospital, which had the
correct and complete address, was returned to sender.
It had the correct street name of the hospital, number, suburb, city, and
postcode, but was required to be marked up as return to sender, no
delivery point.
With no return address on the back, it would've been destroyed by New Zealand Post
if no address was found inside. The sender would not know
it never got to the emergency department of the hospital, and the emergency
department would not know it was ever sent to them.
And this is New Zealand Post policy since May 2024.
In almost every case of an internet search for a postal
address of a main city hospital, the hospital's private bag
or post office number will not be displayed, only the physical street
address.
And so people address their mail to hospital patients as they find the address from
an internet search, and their cards are then to be returned to them.
And this is the policy of New Zealand Post since May 2024.
My brother-in-law here, John Boys, was a hospital chaplain for 25 years,
and he said how important it is in the recovery
process for hospital patients to receive cards and flowers.
Mm-hmm.
New Zealand Post policy since May 2024 is a
cost-saving measure, is to return to sender mail with the
correct postage and addressed in good faith to
existing physical street locations because New Zealand
Post's stated intention is not to extend its delivery
network by adding more street addresses to its database.
Posties around New Zealand continue to disobey New Zealand Post
instructions as they try to get mail delivered and not return to
sender.
Not only the Nelson Police Station and a hospital emergency department,
but we think tens of thousands of letters with clear addresses
and correct postage have been returned to the senders.
The volumes of returned mail have been steadily dropping, either
as more senders know it's important to use the box or private bag
number, or as they instead use the more expensive courier
bags. This is a very blunt, cold,
and uncaring behavior modification program
conducted by a state-owned enterprise answerable to this parliament.
There have been no news media statement of advice of the change in mail
addressing standards from New Zealand Post to the public.
The only news media alerts have come from the Postal Workers Union objecting
to this new policy.
I worked as a postie for 20 years, and like every other postie,
I used a markup book to ensure mail got to the intended recipient.
This was part of the service and factored into the price of a stamp.
However, New Zealand Post now wants to call this a free service and remove it as
cost saving. There is a definition in the Postal Services Act of mail
that could be returned to sender. Mail with a wrong or incomplete
address, or no such number, or illegible address, or
the address couldn't be found.
However, as a cost-cutting exercise, two years ago, New
Zealand Post invented a new classification out for
undeliverable postal items that are to be returned to sender,
and are now calling them non-valid postal address.
That is, mail that would no longer be redirected by the posties
from street addresses to the post office box or private bags where they existed.
There is no definition in the Postal Services Act of what New Zealand
Post calls non-valid postal address,
and any search of valid on the New Zealand Post website
only takes you to the postal codes finder.
So without reading through the full oral submission, there are some questions
that we wanted to pose to the committee.
Does the committee believe that the intention of Parliament
at the passage in-
Well, generally, John, it's up to us for the questions.
Okay. Is it? Oh, okay.
It can be-
Okay.
But, if you want to
summarize what you'd like us to know.
Okay. All right. What we'd like you to consider then perhaps.
Perhaps something for the, couple of points for the committee to consider, if I can
put it like that.
We don't believe that the intention of Parliament at the passage of the
law was that such socially important and sensitive mail could
be returned to sender as a cost-saving exercise.
I'll put it as our considerations, if you like.
Um, well, we're not satisfied that Parliament intended when the act
was passed that a postal operator is able to redefine for
itself what is the usual manner of delivering a postal
article,
um, and then returning it to sender as a undeliverable
postal article.
Um, we're not satisfied that New Zealand Post had the authority by
itself to redefine undeliverable
postal article and to establish a new process for dealing with these
mail items by returning them to sender without recourse to
regulations, which they could have used.
And we're not satisfied that it's acceptable that New Zealand Post's
80-page address standards document does not state
that street address mail will not necessarily be delivered
when there is an existing post office box or private bag, instead
returned to the sender.
And we're not satisfied that, finally, that New Zealand Post is fulfilling
its obligation under the State-Owned Enterprise Act to
be an organization that exhibits a sense of
social responsibility by having regard to the interests of the
community in which it operates,
and by endeavoring to accommodate or encourage these when able to do so
So last year, a number of Christmas cards that you folks sent out to your
constituents were returned to Parliament undelivered because of
New Zealand Post's May 2024 policy.
The union says that an alternative for New Zealand Post, if they don't
want to extend their network, is to revert to the pre-May
2024 usual manner of delivering postal
articles in the interest of the community in which it operates.
This means not continuing to return to sender
mail which has been addressed to the street addresses.
Emergency departments,
retirement villages, medical centers, universities, schools,
lawyers, accountants, government departments, whole range of things.
This Christmas, we don't want to see a number of your Christmas cards,
again, returned to you undelivered, as they were last Christmas,
or Christmas cards addressed to hospital patients
returned to senders undelivered because of a blunt, cold,
and uncaring behavior modification program
introduced by New Zealand Post two years ago.
All right. Thank you, John. We've got time for a couple questions.
Thanks, Chair.
And as much as I'm concerned about
my Christmas card delivery, which I've experienced what you're referring to-
Yeah
... my concern is for the other businesses and organizations
affected.
Yes.
So can you clarify for me, if a postie's going down Victoria Avenue in
Wanganui, for example-
Yep
... and one shop doesn't have a PO box or private
bag you'll deliver there, but the next shop, let's say it's got a
private bag or post office box,
the mail wouldn't be delivered to that shop because they've got a post office box.
Is that-
We've had exactly that example, but not in Wanganui, where there's a block of 10
shops.
Yeah.
And one of the shops has a post office box number, and the postie
was told not to deliver the mail into that shop because it had a
post office box number. When it was addressed to the street address, return it
to sender. He said, "I'm going past, and I want to put it in there," and he was
told he was not to deliver it, but to return it to sender. Exactly that situation.
Much more work.
Right.
Exactly that situation.
Thank you for clarifying. Yeah, that answers my question. Thank you.
All right. Any other-
No, that's good. I'm very interested. Sorry.
No, I have every sympathy for you even though I
shamefully didn't send any Christmas cards.
So they don't come back if you don't send them.
I was just interested in your experience with
street addresses that Google provides sometimes,
or other map services, I don't want to be
too specific, that are then not what the
street address is that the post office has.
All the time, if you want somebody to come here,
are we 1 Museum Street? Are we 1 Molesworth Street?
Are we Parliament Buildings?
Obviously you're not going to have somebody come and meet you at a PO box, but
the experience here
does show real confusion about where the real address
is as well.
Mm.
So how do you manage that side of things?
Well, I think New Zealand Post has picked up on this idea that mail going to
Parliament was being returned to sender.
I understand they've taken steps to make sure that mail addressed to Parliament,
even if it hasn't got a box number or a street number, it's just
maybe Chris here,
maybe Greg here at Parliament Buildings, Wellington-
Is addressed
... it will be directed by New Zealand Post here, even if the address is not
correct. But they're not doing that for hospitals, prisons,
restaurants.
Well, that doesn't seem to be quite fair.
It's not. And that's why the posties are so angry about this, and so are the
customers when they're told their mail is being returned to sender.
When New Zealand Post announced to businesses they were going to do this, they
didn't tell them, "By the way, you can apply for your
street address to be registered as a delivery point." They didn't tell them that.
And posties have said when they encourage businesses to try to
register their street address as a delivery point, they said, "Nobody
gets back to us. We've given up. We can't do it." So it's
clear that New Zealand Post had told us in a written document they do not want to
extend their network, but the result is returning this mail to
sender, which is we are saying, "Okay, go back to marking it up as the
posties have always done because there's a lot fewer to mark up now.
A lot of people have picked up on the box numbers."
All right. We'll have to move on now.
We've got our next submitters coming.
You're welcome to remain at the table, if you'd like, for our next submitters.
I hope all your Christmas cards get to the constituents.
Well, I'm not a Grinch. I still send them out.
That's good. Thank you.
I have confidence in our posties at the moment.
That's great. Thank you.
Reading my email last time.
Can we have, please, New Zealand Post
up on our screen?
Do you want to think
Can I leave the written copies of the submissions here?
Yes, Mr. Kenning. We have you there.
And is Mr. Riordan there, or is it just yourself
today? Matt Riordan. Yeah, he might just be on mute
and there he goes.
Sorry. First time on
Zoom. Can everyone hear me and see me?
First time on Zoom and it's-
Well, sorry. No, that wouldn't be correct. Sorry.
We use a
-
I see. Coming from New Zealand Post, that's probably fair enough.
Yeah.
It's a strategic decision.
I had to install-
Questions. Thank you
Well, firstly, good afternoon, and thank you for the opportunity to attend this
hearing and to speak to the petition that this committee is currently considering.
My name is Matt Reardon. I'm the General Manager for Service Delivery at New
Zealand Post, where I'm responsible for the last mile delivery operation.
With me today is Matthew Kenning, our Government Relations Advisor.
We take it the committee has read our written submission, but I want to
quickly take the opportunity to make a couple of points before taking
questions. The issues raised in the petition relate
to operational changes we started two years ago in
2024, and I'm happy to discuss why we made these
changes. It's well understood that a physical address is not
always the same as a mail delivery address, and that many organizations have
separate postal addresses. The change we made two years ago
simply required mail to be sent to a valid delivery address
and stop the informal process of manually updating addresses when they were
wrong, which was time-consuming, costly, and not always accurate.
If mail items are addressed to a valid postal address and have the correct postage,
then our posties will deliver those mail items.
A valid postal address may include a location near or within a business
premise. We are open to businesses and other organizations asking to
register their physical addresses for delivery if they wish, if they meet our
criteria.
But we find that most don't want delivery to a physical address, such as an
unsecure roadside letterbox, and they prefer their PO box and
private bag.
Where
a mail item has a wrong address or isn't a valid postal address in our
network, we follow the usual return to sender processes.
We felt
like we ran a good process focusing on education for
senders and receivers when we made the change in 2024.
We're happy to take questions.
All right. Celia Wade-Brown.
Thank you. This is
obviously a complicated matter about what an
address is or isn't.
So
can you just clarify the actual process?
If you've got, let's say, three shops in a row, they're number
1 High Street, 2 High Street, 3 High Street.
And you get,
probably from a candidate,
a letter to all of the three.
Where do you know that that shop one,
shop two, or shop three actually also has
a PO box number and therefore shouldn't be delivered?
Or is it that they haven't registered their address and that's
why it's not delivered?
Yeah, really good question. They're actually two separate addresses,
right? And in those examples, the three shops,
two of them or one of them or all of them may actually have both.
They may have a physical address registered with New Zealand Post, and they may
have a postal address, like a PO box, et
cetera. So if mail coming to our posties
turns up, they are typically delivering items to physical
addresses.
Versus if it was sent to a PO box, that's not done
by our posties. That's done by-
No
... yeah.
Sorry. So when the mail
is sorted-
Yes
... to High Street,
I don't know, Whanganui for the sake of argument.
The
addresses are checked off against that physical register?
Yes, we've got an address list of
physical addresses that are registered, so when the mail turns up for those,
the posties will sort them and deliver them.
But there will be a lot of businesses that don't have a physical address
as a mailing item. Now, they can register, and we will look
at the criteria and approve that. But if
not, then that item, and this is the
essence of the petition, traditionally
was marked up by the postie, and
that's the process that we
ceased the historical process and put a new process in place.
And this only
pertains to businesses and institutions, I see.
Yes. It's typically where businesses won't have a letterbox out on
the footpath, or it's difficult for us to
access the building, or they may have somewhere inside where
we could put the mail, therefore, they don't have a registered physical
address.
But the-
And could we ask the special case of hospitals?
So hospitals-
Sorry.
Carl, you've got a question.
Thanks, Chair. I like that question to start, though, and then I've got another
quick question. So why not at a hospital ensure that it's delivered
or, now I understand why the police
Christmas card I sent to the local station in Hawera didn't get delivered, and
I certainly didn't understand this.
And I'm a lover of stamps and have a fondness
of hand-delivered mail, as many of my constituents could attest to.
So why not just deliver it? Why not trust the posties to-
Sure
... do what's right?
So, to answer that question, I'll touch on the
process that we changed, and just so you can
understand why we stopped that process.
And then I'll talk to the options that we have provided
businesses.
So the historic process
was one that was very
manual. It was an informal process
where posties would use their knowledge, and they would sort of cross out
information. They would maintain paper-based lists.
The challenge with that is it wasn't informed by the businesses
And so if a business moved or people moved, our list got
out of date and we could inadvertently send
items to the wrong place. There's also a
commercial element to that as well, but I can sort of come
back at that. So we had a flawed
process that we stopped. We went through, two
years ago,
a big engagement processes with businesses.
It took over a year, three waves of four months each, where
we engaged with them and talked to them about
the changes and communicating with their
senders to get the right addresses.
We also talked about the fact that if they
wanted a hospital, wanted to have a physical delivery, they register.
So through that process, we had 360 businesses register, and we
approved up to about 90% of those. So that physical
delivery option-
Mm
... does exist right now. In addition,
a business can also apply for a permanent redirection, which is a
more robust, sustainable solution of what used to exist,
because that's informed by customers, by the businesses
through a system, and we know we're getting the right things to the
right people and not relying on bits of paper that's outdated.
Sorry, a long-winded response, but I wanted to just take a bit of history through.
Chair, as a supplementary, I think that sounds really interesting and could've
been created on the whiteboard behind you, but I've
been into the mail distribution center in Whanganui, and I'm pretty confident
that my constituents in Whanganui
know when those businesses move and know where they move to.
And I'm pretty sure that that would be
the confidence I would have in your staff, even if you don't, that across
the country, they would know that as well.
And I'm perplexed as to
why, if the Whanganui
Hospital, as an example, didn't register its address because they have more
important things to do,
you wouldn't deliver the card there.
And particularly given it's probably our older constituents who are
still using paper-based cards and the like,
that they would be looking this up.
And certainly, if I don't know it, I can guarantee you a lot of our constituents
don't know it. Just doesn't make sense to me.
Sure. And I've been a postie in the past
myself, and so the challenge with those lists is
that posties can come and go. And those lists, when we actually went
and updated them, we sent letters to 50,000 businesses to
talk to them about the change in the process.
Those lists were grossly out of date.
Because businesses weren't telling us when they moved or shifted or when someone
came in and went out. So the risk of sending an item to the wrong place,
even though the goodwill and the intention was right,
it was really high. Those lists were really inaccurate.
All right. Okay, look, thank you very much. We're going to have to keep moving.
But, yes, we've had two very strong presentations here.
The job of the committee now is that we'll report back on this.
And if there's any further information you require, we'll
make contact with both parties. Thank you very
much.
Thank you.